[
    {
        "question": "Which among the following best describes the word \u201cGrowth\u201d in living organisms?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Increase in mass either due to accumulation or due to changes that body undergoes internally",
            "All living organisms grow throughout their life",
            "Growth is a sufficient characteristic to determine whether an organism is living or non-living"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Increase in mass due to internally cell division and increase in number due to replication are twin characteristic of growth",
        "explanation": "Increase in mass due to internal division and increase in number of organisms are twin characteristics of growth. In non-living organisms increase in mass occurs due to accumulation whereas in living organisms it happens due to the proteins and carbohydrates that we intake. Living organisms except plants grow until certain period of their life and then stop growing. Growth is not a sufficient a characteristic to determine if an organism is living. Sometimes it\u2019s possible that even mountains and sand dunes grow due to an accumulation of sand."
    },
    {
        "question": "Reproduction in Planaria takes place through ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Budding",
            "Binary Fission",
            "Asexual spores"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Fragmentation",
        "explanation": "Planaria uses the method of fragmentation and regeneration to reproduce. Whereas fungi reproduce using spores, amoeba uses binary fission to reproduce and hydra uses budding to reproduce."
    },
    {
        "question": "Reproduction is a sufficient condition to determine whether a thing is living or nonliving",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "If an organism reproduces then it is a living organism. However, it need not be a non-living organism if it doesn\u2019t reproduce. Sometimes it\u2019s possible that organisms stop reproducing after a certain period."
    },
    {
        "question": "Sexual reproduction results in variation of the progeny from the parents",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Since sexual reproduction involves only gene from a single parent which undergoes modifications to produce different traits in the progeny",
            "It is due to variation in the time",
            "Parents decide the traits of the progeny and design them accordingly"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sexual reproduction involves gene from both the parents which undergoes modifications to produce traits that vary from the parent",
        "explanation": "Sexual reproduction involves two parental organisms and the gene from both the organisms are involved which undergo modifications to produce new traits in the progeny."
    },
    {
        "question": "Metabolism means ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "division of cells",
            "sum total of all chemical reactions occurring in our body",
            "production of progeny"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "expansion of cell",
        "explanation": "Metabolism refers to the sum total of all the reactions that occur in an organism. Conversions of chemicals in a living organism are called metabolic reaction."
    },
    {
        "question": "The action that the environment does on an organism is called ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Response",
            "Reflex",
            "Reaction"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Stimuli",
        "explanation": "Every organism responds to the external stimuli that the surrounding has on the organism. For example, a touch me not leaf gets closed when touched and a human being runs away when he sees a lion approaching him."
    },
    {
        "question": "Consciousness and cellular organization of the body are the defining features of living organisms",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "Cellular organization and consciousness are properties that are exclusively meant for living organisms. Therefore, these can be considered as the defining properties of the living organisms."
    },
    {
        "question": "When the reactions that occur in the body are made to happen in laboratory conditions they are said to be ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Metabolic reactions",
            "Oxidation reactions",
            "Reduction reactions"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Living reactions",
        "explanation": "Isolated metabolic reactions in vitro are not living things but are called as living reactions. Sum and total of all the chemical reactions that takes place in an organism are called as Metabolic reactions."
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the following statements pick the statement that best describes a living thing",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "All living things reproduce",
            "Living organisms are those that are self replicating, evolving and self-regulating interactive systems capable of responding to external stimuli",
            "Living organisms are those that depend on AI to take decisions"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Living organisms grow endlessly throughout their life",
        "explanation": "Living organisms are those that are self replicating, evolving and self-regulating interactive systems capable of responding to external stimuli. Sometimes it\u2019s possible that living things don\u2019t reproduce due to few disorders. Also, all living organisms except plants stop growing after a certain period of time."
    },
    {
        "question": "Increase in mass and increase in number are twin characteristics of growth",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "Multicellular organisms grow by cell division, i.e. increase in number which thereby leads to increase in mass."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organism among the following reproduce?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Mules",
            "Worker bees",
            "Infertile human couple"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Fertile human couple",
        "explanation": "Fertile human couple successfully produces offspring but mules, worker bees and an infertile human couple are incapable of reproduction."
    },
    {
        "question": "The sum total of all the chemical reactions occurring in our body known as ______",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Anabolism",
            "Amphibolism",
            "Catabolism"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Metabolism",
        "explanation": "Metabolism is the total set of life-sustaining chemical reactions in organisms. Anabolism is a set of constructive processes. Catabolism is a set of destructive processes. Amphibolism leads to both constructive and destructive outcomes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Living and non-living organisms can be differentiated unexceptionally on the basis of _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Growth",
            "Consciousness",
            "Metabolism"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Reproduction",
        "explanation": "Reproduction is the only criteria by which living and non-living organisms can be differentiated without any exception. Growth is seen in non-living organisms as well. Metabolism can be carried out in-vitro. Consciousness is also present in patients in coma."
    },
    {
        "question": "Pick the man-made non-living thing",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Mountains",
            "Valleys",
            "Rivers"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Books",
        "explanation": "Books are non-living and also manmade whereas mountains, rivers and valleys are non- living but occur naturally."
    },
    {
        "question": "A student wanted to keep a pet rat",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "It did not get the space to move",
            "It did not get sunlight to grow",
            "It did not get food to eat"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It did not get air to breathe",
        "explanation": "The rat couldn\u2019t survive because of the lack of air to breathe. A rat can live without space to move, sunlight and food for a few days."
    },
    {
        "question": "Sun is essential for plants as it provides _____",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Water",
            "Roots",
            "Food"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Energy",
        "explanation": "Sun provides energy to plants. Water has to provided to plants or they obtain it naturally from rain. Roots are a part of the plant body which helps in obtaining food, water and minerals. Plants make their own food."
    },
    {
        "question": "Budding is observed in _____",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Planaria",
            "Amoeba",
            "Protonema of mosses"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Yeast",
        "explanation": "Budding is a method of asexual reproduction observed in lower organisms. Yeast multiply through budding. Planaria, Amoeba and Protonema of mosses multiply respectively through regeneration, binary fission and fragmentation respectively."
    },
    {
        "question": "Growth and reproduction are mutually exclusive events in case of the majority of plants and animals",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "Growth is an increase in mass from inside or outside or both whereas reproduction refers to the production of progenies. Growth takes place in both living and non-living organisms but reproduction is seen only in living beings."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the expansion of ICBN?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "International Code for Biological Naming",
            "Indian Code for Biological Naming",
            "International Council for Biodiversity and Nature"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "International Code for Botanical Nomenclature",
        "explanation": "ICBN stands for International Code for Botanical Nomenclature. ICBN deals with the nomenclature of the plants. International Code for Zoological Nomenclature (ICZN) is responsible for the binomial; nomenclature of animals."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following is involved in the naming of the animals scientifically?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "ICBN",
            "ICAN",
            "ICPN"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "ICZN",
        "explanation": "Animals are named by the principles and criteria provided in International Code for Zoological Nomenclature (ICZN). There is a separate set of rules for the naming of plants called International Code of Botanical Nomenclature (ICBN)."
    },
    {
        "question": "What do you think is the need of nomenclature?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Scientists can use this term in their seminars",
            "Nomenclature is something which is same for all organisms and people need not mention each organism with different names",
            "Nomenclature looks fancier and more technical than regional names"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To have a standard name for an organism instead of having many names in different languages",
        "explanation": "There are different languages and so different regional names for an organism. Therefore, scientists came up with the idea of binomial nomenclature. Binomial nomenclature is introduced to standardize the name of a living organism."
    },
    {
        "question": "A binomial nomenclature consists of _______ and_________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Generic name and Phyla",
            "Class and Phyla",
            "Phyla and Kingdom"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Generic name and specific epithet",
        "explanation": "Generic name and specific epithet are the two parts of a binomial nomenclature. A generic name specifies the genus of an organism and the specific epithet describes the species to which it belongs to."
    },
    {
        "question": "Binomial nomenclature is given by ____________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Charles Darwin",
            "Henry Cavendish",
            "James Chadwick"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Carolous Linnaeus",
        "explanation": "Carolous Linnaeus introduced the system of Binomial Nomenclature. Charles Darwin came up with the theory of evolution. Henry Cavendish is the one who discovered hydrogen. James Chadwick is the one who discovered neutron."
    },
    {
        "question": "Magnifera Indica is the binomial nomenclature of mango",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "Biological names are Latinized or derived from Latin and written in Italics. The genus starts with capital letter while the second component, the specific epithet, starts with small letter."
    },
    {
        "question": "The word \u201cTaxa\u201d means ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Phyla",
            "Genus",
            "Kingdom"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Classification",
        "explanation": "The word \u201cTaxa\u201d means classification. And the study of taxa is called as taxonomy. Taxonomy is the classification of animals into different taxa and helps us to study organisms easily."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following taxa are in their increasing order of their similarities?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Class, Phylum, Kingdom",
            "Genus, Kingdom, Phylum",
            "Specific epithet, Phylum, Genus"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Kingdom, Genus, Specific epithet",
        "explanation": "The increasing orders of similarities among various taxa are: Kingdom<Phylum<Class<Order<Family<Genus<Species"
    },
    {
        "question": "Classification is the main concept behind taxonomy",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "Classification enables us to identify and study organisms easily. Study of classification is called taxonomy. Identification and classification of organisms is the basic concept behind taxonomy."
    },
    {
        "question": "The number of described species of living organisms is _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "1.25 million species",
            "0.5 million species",
            "1.025 million species"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "1.7 million species",
        "explanation": "There are 1.7-1.8 million species of living organisms described on the date. Also, there are 1.25 million species of animals, 0.5 million species of plants and 1.025 million species of insects found and described by scientists."
    },
    {
        "question": "The organisation of the biological world begins with __________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "cellular level",
            "atomic level",
            "organismic level"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "submicroscopic molecular level",
        "explanation": "The biological world organisation begins with the submicroscopic molecular level which further broadens to the cellular level and organismic level. The submicroscopic molecular level consists of proteins, carbohydrates, lipids and nucleic acids organised into organelles of the cell."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following books is not written by Carolus Linnaeus?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Systema Naturae",
            "Species Plantarum",
            "Philosophia Botanica"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Historia Naturalis",
        "explanation": "Historia Naturalis is authored by Pliny the Elder whereas Systema Naturae, Species Plantarum and Philosophia Botanica are written by Linnaeus."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is the Father of New Systematics?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Aristotle",
            "Linnaeus",
            "Theophrastus"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Julian Huxley",
        "explanation": "Sir Julian Huxley is the Father of New Systematics.  Aristotle is the Father of Zoology. Linnaeus is the Father of Taxonomy. Theophrastus is the Father of Botany."
    },
    {
        "question": "A taxon can be defined as _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "a group of related families",
            "a group of related species",
            "the number and type of organisms present on Earth"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "a taxonomic group of any ranking",
        "explanation": "A taxon is a taxonomic group of any ranking whereas a group of related species is the genus and a group of related families is the order. Biodiversity is the number and type of organisms present on Earth."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following is not a code of nomenclature for organisms?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "International Code of Botanical Nomenclature",
            "International Code of Bacteriological Nomenclature",
            "International Code of Zoological Nomenclature"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry",
        "explanation": "International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry is for the nomenclature of organic compounds while the International Code of Botanical Nomenclature, International Code of Bacteriological Nomenclature and International Code of Zoological Nomenclature are the three codes of nomenclature for living organisms."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following takes into account evolutionary relationships between organisms?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Cladistics",
            "Artificial System of Classification",
            "Natural System of classification"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Systematics",
        "explanation": "Systematics considers phylogenetic relationships for classification. Cladistics consists of ancestral and derived characters as the basis of classification, Artificial System of Classification takes into account the morphological characters and Natural System of classification considers the natural similarities and dissimilarities to bring out relationships."
    },
    {
        "question": "Binomial Nomenclature means giving a scientific name consisting of a generic name and a family name",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "Binomial Nomenclature means giving a scientific name consisting of a generic name and a specific epithet."
    },
    {
        "question": "What are taxonomical aids?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Taxonomical aids refer to first aid kids used to treat animals",
            "Taxonomical aids are students who study taxonomy",
            "Taxonomical aids are those which help you to study the anatomy of an organism"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Taxonomical aids are those that help you to identify and classify organisms into their respective taxa",
        "explanation": "Taxonomical aids help you to identify and classify organisms into their respective taxa Herbarium sheets, zoological parks, botanical gardens, museums and keys constitute taxonomical aids."
    },
    {
        "question": "SV Zoological Park is located in _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Pune",
            "Visakhapatnam",
            "Chennai"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Tirupati",
        "explanation": "SV Zoological Park is located in Tirupati and it\u2019s one of the Asia\u2019s largest zoological park Indira Gandhi Zoological park is located in Visakhapatnam. Anna zoological park is located in Chennai. Rajiv Gandhi Zoological Park is located in Pune."
    },
    {
        "question": "Herbarium is a _______",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "store house of all animal specimens",
            "place where fresh plants are kept to attract visitors",
            "a devotional place where people offer their prayers for the sacred trees"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "sheets in which different dried plant specimens pressed against the papers are stored for taxonomical study",
        "explanation": "Herbarium sheets are used to preserve dried plant specimens that are pressed against the sheets and are helpful in taxonomical study. Also these are one of the most familiar taxonomical aids used by taxonomists."
    },
    {
        "question": "Pick the odd one out",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Herbarium",
            "Botanical Garden",
            "Flora"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Zoological Park",
        "explanation": "Zoological parks are taxonomical aids to study and categorize animals. Herbarium, Botanical Garden and Flora are taxonomical aids to study plant kingdom."
    },
    {
        "question": "Lal Bagh botanical garden is located in _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Hyderabad",
            "Delhi",
            "Mumbai"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Bangalore",
        "explanation": "Lal Bagh botanical garden is located in Bangalore. It is one of the oldest botanical garden in the world. Few other famous botanical gardens in the world are at Kew (England), Indian Botanical Garden, Howrah and National Botanical Research Institute, Lucknow."
    },
    {
        "question": "Museums preserve larger animals and birds ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "as skeletons",
            "in giant boxes",
            "by creating an environment that resembles their habitat so that they can survive for a long period"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "by compressing and stuffing them into boxes",
        "explanation": "Larger animals and birds are preserved in museums by compressing them into boxes. In zoological parks, animals are provided with an environment that is similar to their habitat so that they can survive for a long period."
    },
    {
        "question": "The pair of options used in keys to determine the taxonomy of an organism is called ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Doublet",
            "Manuals",
            "Description"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Couplet",
        "explanation": "Taxonomists use keys which provide you with a pair of contrasting options called couplet that finally terminates at the correct taxon of the organism."
    },
    {
        "question": "Information on any of the taxon are provided by _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Manuals",
            "Herbarium sheets",
            "Catalogues"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Monographs",
        "explanation": "Monographs provides is with information on any of the taxon. Manuals help us by providing information on species that are found in an area. Herbarium sheets contain dried plant specimens and information about that plant. Catalogue contains list of species and brief information on each of them."
    },
    {
        "question": "CBD stands for ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Conservation of Bio-diversity",
            "Conference on Bio-diversity",
            "Colloquium on Bio-diversity"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Convention on Biological Diversity",
        "explanation": "Convention on Biological Diversity is a treaty signed in United Nations with a motto to conserve bio-diversity and promote sustainable development."
    },
    {
        "question": "Taxonomical aids help you in identification and classification of organisms",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "Taxonomical aids serve as quick referrals for taxonomical studies. They help us in identification and classification of organism according to their taxonomic categories."
    },
    {
        "question": "The similarities among the taxa decrease as it becomes more inclusive",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "The similarities among the taxa decrease as you go above in the hierarchical classification which becomes more and more inclusive as you go on."
    },
    {
        "question": "The study of relationships among different organisms is called _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Taxonomy",
            "Biology",
            "Systematics"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ornithology",
        "explanation": "Taxonomy is the classification of life forms into different taxa. Biology is the study of life. Systematics is the study of relationships among different organisms. Ornithology is the study of birds."
    },
    {
        "question": "Classes are characterized based on the mode of reproduction, habitat, type of blood in animals",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "Animalia is classified into different classes based on their habitat (land/air/ water), mode of reproduction (eggs/ give birth to young ones) and type of blood (cold-blooded/warm-blooded/hot-blooded)."
    },
    {
        "question": "Sexual reproduction must involve parents from _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Same kingdom",
            "Same phylum",
            "Same genus"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Same species",
        "explanation": "Unlike asexual reproduction, sexual reproduction involves two parent species. Sexual reproduction takes place only when both the parent organisms belong to the same species."
    },
    {
        "question": "Cats and lions belong to the family called ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Canidae",
            "Panthera",
            "Mammalia"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Felidae",
        "explanation": "Panthera refers to the genus to which lion, tiger and leopard belong to. Canidae refers to the family to which wolves, dog, jackals and foxes etc. belong to. Felidae is the family to which lion, tiger, leopard and cats etc. belong to. Mammalia is a class of animals which includes all the milk-feeding animals like dogs, cats, humans, bats etc."
    },
    {
        "question": "The action that the environment does on an organism is called ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Response",
            "Reflex",
            "Reaction"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Stimuli",
        "explanation": "Every organism responds to the external stimuli that the surrounding has on the organism. For example, a touch me not leaf gets closed when touched and a human being runs away when he sees a lion approaching him."
    },
    {
        "question": "A plant kingdom is further classified into phylum",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "The word phylum is particularly used for animal kingdom. A plant kingdom is further classified into divisions. Animals are divided into 2 phyla (vertebrata and non-vertebrata) whereas plants into 2 divisions (Cryptogams and Spermatophytes)."
    },
    {
        "question": "Animal kingdom is classified into different phyla based on ____________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Type of blood they have",
            "Place they live",
            "Food they eat on"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The presence or absence of vertebral column.",
        "explanation": "Animal kingdom is divided into Vertebrata and Non-vertebrata based on the presence or absence of vertebral column. Plants are divided into Cryptogams and Spermatophytes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Pick the odd one out",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Humans",
            "Ape",
            "Monkey"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Cats",
        "explanation": "Humans, ape and monkey belong to the order Primata whereas cats, lion, dogs, tigers belong to the order called Carnivora. But all of the above animals belong to the class of Mammalia."
    },
    {
        "question": "Bats belong to the class ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Chiroptera",
            "Scrotifera",
            "Chordata"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Mammalia",
        "explanation": "Bats belong to the order of Chiroptera, class of Mammalia, clade of Scrotifera and phylum of Chordate. Human beings also belong to the class of mammalian."
    },
    {
        "question": "Potato, Tomato and Brinjal belong to the order called ______________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Solanum",
            "Solanaceae",
            "Convolvulacae"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Polymonioles",
        "explanation": "Potato, Tomato and Brinjal belong to the genus Solanum, family Solanaceae and order Polymonioles. Plant families like Convolvulacae are also included in the order of Polymonioles."
    },
    {
        "question": "Orders are grouped to form a __________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Family",
            "Genus",
            "Phylum"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Class",
        "explanation": "Genus includes all the related species. Related genera constitute a family. Related families constitute an order. Related orders constitute a class. Related classes constitute a phylum. Related phyla constitute a kingdom."
    },
    {
        "question": "German Shepherd, Chihuahua, Pug, Basenji belongs to ___________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Same genus",
            "Same family",
            "Same class"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Same species",
        "explanation": "German Shepherd, Chihuahua, Pug, Poodle, Beagle, Basenji are different breeds of dog. Irrespective of the breed of the dog they belong to the same species i.e. Lupus Familaris."
    },
    {
        "question": "Panthera Pardus is the binomial nomenclature of leopard",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "Binomial nomenclature of any organism contains of two parts namely specific epithet and generic epithet. A generic epithet starts with a capital letter and a specific epithet should start with a small letter with both of them being separated by a gap. A binomial nomenclature should be written in italics. But here it is not written in italics and the starting letter in pardus is written in capitals. The binomial nomenclature of leopard is"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pick the incorrect statement",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Binomial nomenclature has two parts namely generic epithet and specific epithet and also some descriptive information along with them",
            "Binomial nomenclature helps you to identify the relationship between animals",
            "Binomial nomenclature is introduced in order to avoid ambiguity that is arises due to different names for a same animal in different languages"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The rules for binomial nomenclature are set by IUCN",
        "explanation": "The rules for binomial nomenclature for animals are set by International Union for Zoological Nomenclature (IUZN) and for plants by International Union for Botanical Nomenclature (IUBN). Binomial nomenclature has two parts namely generic epithet and specific epithet written in italics. Sometimes it might also contain description regarding the scientist. It helps you to track the evolutionary relationships of organisms."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following is not a rule for writing binomial nomenclature?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "All the words in the binomial nomenclature should either be Latinized or should be derived from Latin",
            "Binomial nomenclature may contain description about the organism",
            "The first part of the binomial nomenclature contains the generic name and the second part contains the specific epithet"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The generic epithet should start with capital letter and specific epithet should start with small letter with a hyphen separating them",
        "explanation": "The generic epithet should start with capital letter and specific epithet should start with small letter with a gap separating them. Nomenclature should be either derived from Latin or should be Latinized. It may also contain description about the organism like the name of the scientist who has done major works related to that organism."
    },
    {
        "question": "Aristotle classified the organisms based on their _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Cell wall",
            "Evolutionary relationships",
            "Method of reproduction"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Morphological characteristics",
        "explanation": "Aristotle classified the organisms based on their morphological characteristics. His classification neglected characteristics like nature of the cell wall, evolutionary relationships and method of reproduction."
    },
    {
        "question": "Aristotle\u2019s classification of plants is based on the ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Flowering or non-flowering",
            "Number of cotyledons present",
            "Type of roots they have"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Size",
        "explanation": "Aristotle classified plants based on their size into herbs (Wheat, Paddy, etc.), shrubs (Rose, Jasmine, etc.) and trees (Banyan, Banana, etc.). He classified animals based on their blood."
    },
    {
        "question": "Aristotle\u2019s classification contained ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "5 Kingdoms",
            "3 Kingdoms",
            "4 Kingdoms"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "2 Kingdoms",
        "explanation": "Aristotle\u2019s classification contained two kingdoms i.e. Plants and Animals. Plants are sub-divided into herbs, shrubs and tree. Animals are further sub-divided into red blooded and non- red blooded animals."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Aristotle classified the organisms into 5 kingdoms",
            "Aristotle\u2019s classification helped in classifying every organism",
            "It considered the method of reproduction of an organism"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It didn\u2019t consider the cell structure of the organism",
        "explanation": "Aristotle classified the organisms into two kingdoms namely, Plants and Animals. It didn\u2019t classify organisms like bacteria, fungi and viruses. It didn\u2019t consider the cell structure, method of reproduction and evolutionary relationships."
    },
    {
        "question": "Linnaeus classified organisms into ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Prokaryotes and Eukaryotes",
            "Monera and Protista",
            "Bacteria and Non-bacteria"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Plantae and Animalia",
        "explanation": "Aristotle classified the organisms into Plants and Animals whereas Carolus Linnaeus classified the organisms into Plantae and Animalia. Whittaker\u2019s 5 kingdom classification contained Monera, Protista, Fungi, Plantae and Animalia."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following is a major disadvantage of the Linnaeus and Aristotle\u2019s classification?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "It is based on the morphological characteristics",
            "It considered the evolutionary relationships of the organisms",
            "They managed to include almost every organism in their classification"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "These classifications resulted in organisms that are of completely different in the same group",
        "explanation": "Linnaeus and Aristotle\u2019s classification is based on the morphological characteristics of the plants and animals. This classification resulted in classification of organisms like fungi and humans that completely different in the same group."
    },
    {
        "question": "Linnaeus classified organisms based on their cell structure",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "Linnaeus didn\u2019t consider the cell structure of organisms (prokaryotes and eukaryotes) in order to classify them. Linnaeus classification is based on the morphological characteristics of organisms."
    },
    {
        "question": "Linnaeus classified amoeba under _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Protista",
            "Monera",
            "Plantae"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Animalia",
        "explanation": "Linnaeus classified amoeba under Animalia. His classification didn\u2019t consider cell structure, nature of the cell wall, mode of reproduction, evolutionary relationships which resulted amoeba in Animalia."
    },
    {
        "question": "Classification of organisms by Linnaeus and Aristotle didn\u2019t include many organisms",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "Classification of organisms by Linnaeus and Aristotle didn\u2019t include many organisms like fungi, bacteria and viruses into either of the kingdoms. Instead they were forced to come under either of these."
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Aristotle Chlorella comes under _______",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Plantae",
            "Animalia",
            "Protista"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Plants",
        "explanation": "Aristotle classified organisms as Plants and Animals. He considered Chlorella under the category of Plants. His classification didn\u2019t consider structure of the cell which resulted in Chlorella under Plants in his classification."
    },
    {
        "question": "Whittaker classified organisms based on their cell structure, mode of nutrition and method of reproduction",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "Whittaker classified organism into 5 kingdoms based on their cell structure, mode of nutrition, method of reproduction and evolutionary relations namely, Monera, Protista, Fungi, Plantae and Animalia."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Whittaker\u2019s 5 kingdom classification, all the prokaryotic organisms are grouped under ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Protista",
            "Fungi",
            "Animalia"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Monera",
        "explanation": "In Whittaker\u2019s 5 kingdom classification, all the prokaryotic organisms are grouped under Monera; all the unicellular organisms under Protista and all the fungi form a separate Kingdom. So, Whittaker\u2019s 5 kingdom classification managed to include characteristics like nature and structure of cells."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Whittaker\u2019s 5 kingdom classification, all the unicellular organisms are categorised under ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Protista",
            "Monera",
            "Animals"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Porifera",
        "explanation": "In Whittaker\u2019s 5 kingdom classification, all the unicellular organisms are categorised under Protista. For example, Amoeba, Paramecium, Chlorella and Chlamydomanas fall under the category of Protista."
    },
    {
        "question": "Cell wall in fungi is made up of ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Cellulose",
            "Amino acids",
            "Proteins"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Chitin",
        "explanation": "Cell wall in fungi is made up of chitin. In plants, the cell wall is made up of Cellulose. Whittaker\u2019s classification managed to consider the nature of cell wall which resulted in Fungi and Plants forming two different kingdoms."
    },
    {
        "question": "Chlamydomanas is grouped under________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Monera",
            "Plantae",
            "Fungi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Protista",
        "explanation": "Chlamydomanas is a unicellular organism and so came under the category of Protista. Whittaker\u2019s classification managed in grouping all the unicellular organisms under the category of Protista."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following don\u2019t contain nuclear membrane?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Protista",
            "Fungi",
            "Animalia"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Monera",
        "explanation": "In eukaryotes, all the cell organelles are separated by a membrane. This membrane is absent in prokaryotes. Whittaker classified all the prokaryotes under the kingdom Monera. So, nuclear membrane is absent in Monera."
    },
    {
        "question": "Whittaker\u2019s 5 kingdom classification failed to include Viruses",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "Although Whittaker managed to consider cell structure, nature of the cell, mode of nutrition and method of reproduction in his classification he failed to include viruses in his classification."
    },
    {
        "question": "All the heterotrophic plants are categorized under ____________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Protista",
            "Monera",
            "Plantae"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Fungi",
        "explanation": "In Whittaker\u2019s 5 kingdom classification all the heterotrophic plants are categorized under Fungi. For example, mushrooms, hypomycetes etc. Fall under the category of fungi."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following are incorrect?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Whittaker\u2019s classification managed to consider cell structure, nature of the cell wall, mode of nutrition and method of reproduction",
            "Whittaker\u2019s classification is polyphyletic and so failed to group similar organism under the same kingdom",
            "Whittaker\u2019s classification didn\u2019t include viruses"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "In 2 kingdom classification, all the fungi and algae are forcefully made to join Animalia",
        "explanation": "Whittaker\u2019s classification managed to consider cell structure, nature of the cell wall, mode of nutrition and method of reproduction. In 2 kingdom classification, all the fungi and algae are forcefully made to join Plantae. Whittaker\u2019s classification is polyphyletic and so failed to group similar organism under the same kingdom. Whittaker\u2019s classification didn\u2019t include viruses."
    },
    {
        "question": "Plantae consists of _______",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Prokaryotes",
            "Unicellular organisms",
            "Heterotrophs"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Multi-cellular organism",
        "explanation": "Plantae consists of Eukaryotes that are multi-cellular and autotrophic i.e. all the organisms in Plantae have multiple cells that contain membranous cell organelles and also can prepare their own food."
    },
    {
        "question": "Monera comprises of prokaryotic organisms like bacteria which are the oldest life forms of the earth",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "All the prokaryotic organisms are grouped under Monera. Bacteria are classified based on their shape as Coccus, Bacillus, Vibrium and Spirillum."
    },
    {
        "question": "Dunaliella salina belongs to the category of ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Thermophiles",
            "Hydrophiles",
            "Methanogens"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Halophiles",
        "explanation": "Dunaliella salina belongs to the category of Halophiles. Halophiles can survive in areas which are highly concentrated in salt. Thermophiles can survive in conditions with high temperature. Methanogens are responsible for production of methane."
    },
    {
        "question": "Methanogens are present in the ______",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Mouth of cow",
            "Respiratory system of cow",
            "Ribs of a cow"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Guts of cow",
        "explanation": "Methanogens are responsible for production of methane. These are present in marshy areas like guts of a cow which helps in production of biogas from cow dung."
    },
    {
        "question": "Archaebacteria can survive in extreme conditions because of the ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "complex metabolic reactions in their body",
            "fact that they are the oldest life forms on the earth",
            "double membrane nucleus"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "rigid cell wall they have",
        "explanation": "Archaebacteria have a rigid cell wall which helps them to survive in extreme conditions like high salt concentration (halophiles) and very high temperature (thermophiles)."
    },
    {
        "question": "In chemosynthetic autotrophs energy to prepare food is obtained from __________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Light energy",
            "Bio-energy",
            "Thermal energy"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Chemical energy",
        "explanation": "Bacteria adopt different modes of nutrition like photosynthetic, chemosynthetic, saprophytic and parasitic. Chemosynthetic autotrophs prepare their own food by obtaining energy from organic substances."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following is incorrect about Cyanobacteria?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "The word cyano means greenish-blue because of which cyanobacteria is also called as blue-green algae",
            "The colour of cyanobacteria is due to presence of chlorophyll",
            "Cyanobacteria help in enriching oxygen levels in the atmosphere"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Cyanobacteria are chemosynthetic autotrophs",
        "explanation": "Cyanobacteria contain chlorophyll which helps to perform photosynthesis and in turn enrich the oxygen levels in the atmosphere. The word \u201ccyano\u201d in cyanobacteria means blue-green algae and therefore they are also called as blue-green algae."
    },
    {
        "question": "Pseudomonas adopt ___________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Parasitic mode of nutrition",
            "Saprophytic mode of nutrition",
            "Autotrophic mode of nutrition"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Heterotrophic mode of nutrition",
        "explanation": "Parasites obtain food from the host. Heterotrophs obtain food from autotrophs. Saprophytes feed on dead and decay matter. Autotrophs prepare their own food either by using light energy or chemical energy. Pseudomonades are Heterotrophs."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following are incorrect about Mycoplasma?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "It adopts parasitic mode of nutrition",
            "It is present in urogenital tract and blood smears",
            "Mycoplasma is the smallest living cell"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It has rigid cell wall",
        "explanation": "Mycoplasma has no cell wall. It is parasite and is present in urogenital tract and blood smears. They are the smallest living cells and are capable of causing diseases."
    },
    {
        "question": "E",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Respiratory tract of humans",
            "Urogenital tract of humans",
            "Excretory tract of humans"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Digestive tract of humans",
        "explanation": "Escherichia coli is a rod-shaped bacterium present in the digestive tract of warm-blooded animals like human beings and is responsible for the indigestion problems in humans."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following is incorrect about Lacto bacilli?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "These are rod shaped bacteria",
            "These are the bacteria responsible for turning milk into curd",
            "They are also useful in industries for fermentation of wine"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "These are parasites",
        "explanation": "Lacto bacilli, as the name says, are rod shaped bacteria that are responsible for turning milk into curd. They adopt heterotrophic mode of nutrition. These are also useful in fermentation of wine."
    },
    {
        "question": "Bacteria reproduce by ___________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Sexual reproduction",
            "Asexual reproduction",
            "Spores"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sexual reproduction and asexual reproduction",
        "explanation": "Bacteria reproduce either by asexual reproduction or sometimes adopt sexual mode of reproduction. In sexual reproduction they mainly adopt conjugation in which DNA transfer takes place from one bacterium to other. In asexual reproduction they undergo binary fission."
    },
    {
        "question": "Protists survive in ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "dry desert",
            "dry mountains",
            "hot hills"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "aquatic regions",
        "explanation": "Protists survive in aquatic regions. They can either survive in fresh water lakes, large oceans, deep seas and marshy areas etc. This is because their body is adapted to survive in areas with low oxygen concentration."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following comprises of animal like protists?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Chrysophytes",
            "Slime molds",
            "Dianoflagellates"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Protozoans",
        "explanation": "Since, Protozoans are mobile and can ingest food into their body they resemble animals. Some of the protozoans follow holozoic nutrition like that of animals. Therefore, Protozoans are animal like protists."
    },
    {
        "question": "Diatoms are grouped under _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Protozoans",
            "Dianoflagelletes",
            "Euglenoids"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Chrysophytes",
        "explanation": "Diatoms are grouped under Chrysophytes. Chrysophytes comprise of golden algae, diatoms and plant like protists etc. It\u2019s because of the golden-yellow color of the species they are named as Chrysophytes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Cell wall in diatoms is made of _______",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Chitin",
            "Pectin",
            "Cellulose"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Silica",
        "explanation": "Cell wall in diatoms is made up of Silica. It\u2019s a double shelled cell wall that fits exactly into each other like the lid of a box. Cell wall of diatoms remains in the earth even after they die and accumulate to form diatomaceous earth."
    },
    {
        "question": "Diatomaceous earth can be used as a pest control because _________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "it is porous",
            "it contains silica which is poisonous for pests when eaten and therefore they die",
            "it acts as anesthesia when given in minor quantities but pests die when large quantities are in taken"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "it snatches out lipids from the outermost waxy layer of pests called cuticle and makes them dry which results in their death",
        "explanation": "Diatomaceous earth is used in pest control and grain storage. This is because they are abrasive in nature which snatches out lipids from the outermost layer of pests called cuticle and makes them dry which results in their death."
    },
    {
        "question": "Diatoms store food as _______",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Starch",
            "Glucose",
            "Fructose"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Oil",
        "explanation": "Diatoms store food as oil. Plants store their food as starch. Diatoms are the main food producing bodies in oceans. They prepare food by photosynthesis."
    },
    {
        "question": "Chrysophytes contain chlorophyll or carotene or xanthophyll in them",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "Chrysophytes contain chlorophyll or carotene or xanthophyll in them. Chrysophytes attain color due to these pigments present in them. Their cell wall is rigid and is made up of Cellulose/ Pectin/ Silica."
    },
    {
        "question": "Cell wall in dianoflagelllates contain _______",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Chitin",
            "Silica",
            "Pectin"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Cortex",
        "explanation": "Dianoflagellates have a complex cell wall made up of cortex. They also possess light sensitive organelle in their cell. Eye spot is found in some of them. Erythropsidium is known to have smallest eye."
    },
    {
        "question": "Dianoflagellates contain ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "two flagella with both being transversal",
            "two flagella with both being longitudinal",
            "three flagella with one being along x-axis, other being along y-axis and the third one being along z-axis"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "two flagella with lone being longitudinal and other being transversal",
        "explanation": "Dianoflagellates contain two flagella with lone being longitudinal and other being transversal. These two flagella help them for their movement and rotation."
    },
    {
        "question": "Dianoflagellates are plant like protists",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "Dianoflagellates are neither plant nor animal like protists. This is because they perform both photosynthesis and locomotion. Therefore, they are neither plants nor animals."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is red tide?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Accumulation of cell wall deposits of red algae is called red tide",
            "Accumulation of red blood cells in water",
            "Spread of chrysophytes due to rapid reproduction"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Coloration of water due to rapid multiplication of red dianoflagellates",
        "explanation": "Red tide is the coloration of water due to very rapid multiplication of red dianoflagellates. Chemicals released due to this rapid growth are harmful for aquatic life."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following is responsible for red tide?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Udinium",
            "Noctiluca",
            "Golden algae"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Gonyaulax",
        "explanation": "Red tide is the coloration of water due to very rapid multiplication of red dianoflagellates like Gonyaulax. Chemicals released due to this rapid growth are harmful for aquatic life."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following belong to plankton?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Dianoflagellates",
            "Euglenoids",
            "Protozoans"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Chrysophytes",
        "explanation": "Chrysophytes are found in aquatic habitats. They are present in fresh water as well as marine. Chrysophytes Are microscopic in nature and float in water currents like planktons."
    },
    {
        "question": "Protists are unicellular eukaryotes",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "All the unicellular eukaryotes are placed in Protista. But all protists are not unicellular. There are few protists that are multi-cellular. But all the protists are eukaryotic organisms."
    },
    {
        "question": "Desmids belong to ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Dianoflagellates",
            "Euglenoids",
            "Protozoans"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Chrysophytes",
        "explanation": "Chrysophytes comprise of diatoms and golden algae (desmids). Desmids are unicellular eukaryotes and can prepare their own food by photosynthesis. Desmids reproduce both by sexually and asexually."
    },
    {
        "question": "Where does the energy required to carry life processes come from?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "House",
            "Earth",
            "Galaxy"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Food",
        "explanation": "All the energy required for life processes is obtained by the oxidation of some macromolecules that we call as food. All living organisms need energy to carry out daily life activities."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following can synthesise their food?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Yellow plants",
            "Animals",
            "Mycoplasma"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Green plants",
        "explanation": "Only green plants and cyanobacteria can prepare their food, by the process of photosynthesis. They trap light energy and convert it into chemical energy that is stored in the bonds of carbohydrates."
    },
    {
        "question": "What kind of organisms are fungi?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Carnivores",
            "Omnivores",
            "Herbivores"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Saprophytes",
        "explanation": "Fungi are generally saprophytes which are dependent on dead and decaying matter. Animals are heterotrophic, i.e., they obtain food from plants directly (herbivores) or indirectly (carnivores)."
    },
    {
        "question": "In green plants, all the cells, tissues and organs carry out photosynthesis",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "In green plants, not all cells, tissues and organs photosynthesise, only cells containing chloroplasts, that are most often located in the superficial layers, carry out photosynthesis."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is meant by cellular respiration?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Breakdown of water",
            "Breakdown of air to consume energy",
            "Breakdown of soil to release energy"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Breakdown of food materials to release energy",
        "explanation": "Cellular respiration is the mechanism of breakdown of food materials within the cell to release energy and the trapping of this energy for the synthesis of ATP."
    },
    {
        "question": "Where does the photosynthesis take place in eukaryotes?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Mitochondria",
            "Cytoplasm",
            "Vacuoles"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Chloroplasts",
        "explanation": "Photosynthesis takes place within the chloroplasts in the eukaryotes whereas the breakdown of complex molecules to yield energy takes place in the cytoplasm and the mitochondria."
    },
    {
        "question": "The breaking of which of the following bonds leads to release of energy?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "P-P bonds",
            "N-N bonds",
            "S-S bonds"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "C-C bonds",
        "explanation": "The breaking of the C-C bonds of complex compounds through oxidation within the cells, leads to the release of a considerable amount of energy. This process is known as respiration."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following compounds are not oxidised to release energy?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Proteins",
            "Fats",
            "Carbohydrates"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "DNA",
        "explanation": "Nucleic acids like DNA and RNA are never oxidised to release energy because these are integrated parts of the cell and they are used to carry or express different genes in the human beings which carry out different functions like the formation of proteins, fats and carbohydrates."
    },
    {
        "question": "During oxidation within a cell, all the energy is released into a single step",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "During oxidation within a cell, all the energy contained in the respiratory substrate is not released in a single step because then all the energy would be lost in a single step and the cell would not be able to store the synthesised energy for its future use."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following acts as the energy currency of the cell?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Enzymes",
            "Proteins",
            "DNA"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "ATP",
        "explanation": "ATP or Adenosine Triphosphate acts as the energy currency of the cell. The energy which is released by the oxidation of respiratory substrates is stored in ATP so that we can use it for future purposes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is used as a precursor for the biosynthesis of other molecules?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Phosphorous substrate",
            "Nitrogen substrates",
            "Sulphur skeletons"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Carbon skeletons",
        "explanation": "Carbon skeletons are used as precursors for the biosynthesis of other biomolecules as the oxidation of these carbon skeletons leads to the formation of ATP which is stored by the cells to be utilised in various-energy requiring processes of the organisms."
    },
    {
        "question": "By the use of which of the following structures, plants exchange gases?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Stem",
            "Root",
            "Bark"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Stomata",
        "explanation": "Plants, unlike animals, have no specialised organs for gaseous exchange but they use stomata and lenticels for this purpose. Plants can easily get along without any specialised respiratory organs."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why plants can get along without the need for specialised respiratory organs?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "It would be an extra expense",
            "They don\u2019t like it",
            "Oxygen is easily available for all the parts of the plants"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Each plant part takes care of its own needs",
        "explanation": "There are several reasons why plants can get along without respiratory organs."
    },
    {
        "question": "What are lenticels?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Openings on the surface of roots",
            "Pores on leaves",
            "Pores on stem"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Openings on the surface of the bark",
        "explanation": "In stems, the living cells are organised in thin layers inside and beneath the bark. They also have openings called lenticels. The cells in the interior are dead and only provide mechanical support."
    },
    {
        "question": "How many types of movement do the cells of the human body exhibit?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "4",
            "1",
            "2"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "3",
        "explanation": "The human body has various types of cells which have different morphologies and perform specific functions. The cells have mainly three types of movement- amoeboid, ciliary and muscular."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is not a type of movement mainly shown by cells of the human body?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Amoeboid",
            "Ciliary",
            "Muscular"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Flagellar",
        "explanation": "The human body has various types of cells which perform various functions. The most common types of movements seen are amoeboid, ciliary and muscular. Flagellar locomotion is rare in human cells."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these cells can be found in blood?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Islet cells",
            "Zymogenic cells",
            "Thymocytes"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Macrophages",
        "explanation": "Macrophages can be found in blood as well as in various tissues of the body. They are phagocytic cells that show amoeboid movement. Macrophages can especially be found at sites of infection."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these cells show amoeboid movement?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Ciliated epithelia",
            "Columnar epithelia",
            "Squamous epithelia"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Macrophages",
        "explanation": "Macrophages show amoeboid movement. They can be found in blood as well as in various tissues of the body. Epithelia do not usually show such movement. Ciliated epithelia show ciliary movement."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which blood corpuscle exhibits amoeboid locomotion?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Erythrocytes",
            "Thrombocytes",
            "Blood platelets"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Leucocytes",
        "explanation": "The three types of blood corpuscles are erythrocytes or red blood cells, leucocytes or white blood cells and thrombocytes or blood platelets. Leucocytes or white blood cells show amoeboid movement."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these structures is used to carry out amoeboid movement?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Pili",
            "Flagella",
            "Cilia"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Pseudopodia",
        "explanation": "The human body has various types of cells which perform various functions. The most common types of movements seen are amoeboid, ciliary and muscular. Amoeboid movement is carried out by pseudopodia."
    },
    {
        "question": "Where does pseudopodia arise from?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Nucleoplasm",
            "Cell membrane",
            "Nuclear membrane"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Protoplasm",
        "explanation": "The most common types of movements seen in cells of the human body are amoeboid, ciliary and muscular. Amoeboid movement is carried out by pseudopodia, which are formed from the protoplasm."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these structures are involved in amoeboid movement?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Cilia",
            "Pili",
            "Flagella"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Microfilaments",
        "explanation": "The most common types of movements seen in cells of the human body are amoeboid, ciliary and muscular. Amoeboid movement makes use of pseudopodia and cytoskeletal elements such as microfilaments."
    },
    {
        "question": "Epithelia of the trachea show ciliary movement",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "The inner surface of the trachea is lined by ciliary epithelium. Ciliary epithelium shows ciliary movement. This movement drives the dust particles which are inhaled by us, away from the lungs."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these do not show ciliary movement?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Inner lining of trachea",
            "Oviducts",
            "Vasa efferentia"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vas deferens",
        "explanation": "The ciliated epithelium of the inner surface of the trachea, the movement of ova through the oviducts and the vasa efferentia show ciliary movement. The vas deferens does not show ciliary movement."
    },
    {
        "question": "The passage of ova through oviducts involves what type of movement?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Muscular",
            "Flagellar",
            "Amoeboid"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ciliary",
        "explanation": "The most common types of movements seen in cells of the human body are amoeboid, ciliary and muscular. The passage of ova through oviducts involves ciliary movement due to the presence of cilia."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these statements is false regarding trachea?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Some cells show ciliary movement",
            "Foreign particles are directed towards the throat",
            "Ciliated epithelium direct dust away from the bronchi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The inner lining is made of pseudostratified columnar epithelium",
        "explanation": "The inner lining of the trachea is made of ciliated epithelium. the ciliated epithelia show ciliary movement. This movement helps in directing dust and various foreign particles away from the lungs."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these systems do not influence locomotion?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Neural",
            "Muscular",
            "Skeletal"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Integumentary",
        "explanation": "The neural system, the muscular system and the skeletal system influence locomotion and the coordinated activity of these systems is required for locomotion. The integumentary system does not influence it."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which property of muscles is used for locomotion?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Excitability",
            "Extensibility",
            "Elasticity"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Contractility",
        "explanation": "The most common types of movements seen in cells of the human body are amoeboid, ciliary and muscular. Muscular movement relies on the contractile property of muscles, which is essential for locomotion."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these do not involve flagellar movement?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Swimming of spermatozoa",
            "Maintenance of water current in sponges",
            "Locomotion of some protozoans"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Movement of macrophages in blood",
        "explanation": "The movement of macrophages in blood does not involve the use of flagella. Macrophages are phagocytic in nature and are a part of the immune system. They show amoeboid movement."
    },
    {
        "question": "What percentage of body weight of an adult human is contributed by muscles?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "20-30%",
            "10-20%",
            "30-40%"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "40-50%",
        "explanation": "40-50% of the total body weight of an adult human is contributed by muscles. Muscles are required for numerous processes of the body in order to survive and locomote. They are of mesodermal origin."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is not a property of muscles?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Extensibility",
            "Excitability",
            "Elasticity"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Degradability",
        "explanation": "40-50% of the total body weight of an adult human is contributed by muscles. Muscles have several properties such as elasticity, extensibility, excitability and contractibility. Degradability is not a property."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is not a basis of classification for muscles?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Appearance",
            "Location",
            "Regulation of activities"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Excitability",
        "explanation": "Muscles have several properties such as elasticity, extensibility, excitability and contractibility. Muscles can be classified on the basis of appearance, location and regulation of activities."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these statements is not true regarding skeletal muscles?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "They are also called voluntary muscles",
            "They have striations",
            "They are involved in changing of body posture"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "They help in the movement of food through the oesophagus",
        "explanation": "Skeletal muscles are also known as voluntary muscles. They have striations and are also known as striated muscles. They are involved in changing of body posture but not in the movement of food through the oesophagus."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is not a characteristic of cardiac muscles?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "They work continuously",
            "They are branched",
            "They are involuntary"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "They are not striated",
        "explanation": "Cardiac muscles are the muscles of the heart. Cardiac muscles are involuntary muscles that work continuously to pump blood throughout the body. They are branched and are striated in appearance."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is fascia made of?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Keratin",
            "Microtubules",
            "Muscle fibres"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Collagen",
        "explanation": "Fascia is a layer of connective tissue that surrounds the fascicles or muscle bundles in a muscle. It is made out of collagen. Each muscle bundle contains a number of muscle fibres or muscle cells."
    },
    {
        "question": "A muscle fibre is a syncytium",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "A muscle fibre or a muscle cell possesses many nuclei or is multinucleated. Hence, it is a syncytium. A number of muscle fibres or muscle cells are grouped together into a muscle bundle or fascicle."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these ions are abundant in the sarcoplasmic reticulum?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Magnesium",
            "Sodium",
            "Potassium"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Calcium",
        "explanation": "The sarcoplasmic reticulum is the endoplasmic reticulum present in the sarcoplasm of the muscle cell or the muscle fibre. The sarcoplasmic reticulum contains a large number of calcium ions."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these structures has alternate dark and light bands on it?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Fascicles",
            "Sarcolemma",
            "Fascia"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Myofibrils",
        "explanation": "Each muscle cell or muscle fibre contains filaments in its sarcoplasm which are arranged in a parallel manner. These filaments are known as myofibrils and they have alternate dark and light bands."
    },
    {
        "question": "What does the A band of a myofibril contain?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Troponin",
            "Actin",
            "Tropomyosin"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Myosin",
        "explanation": "The A band or anisotropic band contains the protein myosin. The A band is also known as the dark band. The light bands, also called the I bands or the isotropic bands contain the protein actin."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these statements is false regarding myofibrils?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Myosin is parallel to the longitudinal axis of myofibril",
            "Light bands contain actin",
            "Anisotropic bands contain myosin"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The A band is also known as the light band",
        "explanation": "Actin and myosin lie parallel to the longitudinal axis of the myofibril and also to each other. The A band or the anisotropic band or the dark band contains myosin while the light band contains actin."
    },
    {
        "question": "Actin filaments are thicker than myosin filaments",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "Actin and myosin lie parallel to the longitudinal axis of the myofibril and also to each other. The A band contains myosin while the light band contains actin. Actin filaments are thinner than myosin filaments."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is present in the centre of each \u2018I\u2019 band?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "\u2018H\u2019 line",
            "\u2018A\u2019 line",
            "\u2018M\u2019 line"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "\u2018Z\u2019 line",
        "explanation": "The \u2018I\u2019 band or the isotropic band is also known as the light band. It contains the protein actin. The \u2018Z\u2019 line is present in the centre of each \u2018I\u2019 band which bisects it. The \u2018Z\u2019 line is an elastic fibre."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these structures holds myosin filaments together?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "\u2018H\u2019 line",
            "\u2018A\u2019 line",
            "\u2018Z\u2019 line"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "\u2018M\u2019 line",
        "explanation": "The myosin filaments or the thick filaments are held together by the \u2018M\u2019 line. The \u2018M\u2019 line is present in the middle of the \u2018A\u2019 band or the anisotropic band or the dark band, and is thin and fibrous."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is found at the two ends of a sarcomere?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "\u2018H\u2019 line",
            "\u2018A\u2019 line",
            "\u2018M\u2019 line"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "\u2018Z\u2019 line",
        "explanation": "The two ends of a sarcomere or a contractile unit of a muscle is marked by the presence of \u2018Z\u2019 lines. It contains one whole \u2018A\u2019 band or anisotropic band and half of an \u2018I\u2019 band or isotropic band."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is not a component of the thin filament?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Tropomyosin",
            "Troponin",
            "\u2018F\u2019 actin"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "LMM",
        "explanation": "The thin filament or the actin filament is composed of two filaments of \u2018F\u2019 actin wound helically to each other. \u2018F\u2019 actin is a polymer of monomeric \u2018G\u2019 actins. The proteins troponin and tropomyosin are also present."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is present in the globular head of meromyosin?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Troponin",
            "Tropomyosin",
            "LMM"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "ATPase",
        "explanation": "Each thick filament is made of meromyosins, which are monomeric proteins. Each meromyosin has a globular head with a short arm and a tail. The globular head of the meromyosin is an ATPase."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these constitute a motor unit?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Motor neuron + fascia",
            "Motor neuron + muscle",
            "Motor neuron + muscle bundle"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Motor neuron + muscle fibres",
        "explanation": "Muscle fibres connected to a motor neuron make up a motor unit. The motor neuron carries an impulse from the CNS or the central nervous system which stimulates the muscle to contract."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is a neurotransmitter?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "HMM",
            "Troponin",
            "ATPase"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Acetylcholine",
        "explanation": "Acetylcholine is a neurotransmitter. It is a chemical compound that helps in the transmission of signals or impulses to and from the CNS or the central nervous system via the neurons."
    },
    {
        "question": "What does acetylcholine generate in the sarcolemma?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Resting potential",
            "Graded potential",
            "Membrane potential"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Action potential",
        "explanation": "Acetylcholine is a neurotransmitter. It is a chemical compound that helps in the transmission of impulses. Acetylcholine generates action potential in the sarcolemma which spreads through the muscle fibre."
    },
    {
        "question": "\u2018F\u2019 actin is a polymer of \u2018G\u2019 actins",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "\u2018F\u2019 actin is a polymer of \u2018G\u2019 or globular actins which are monomers. Two \u2018F\u2019 or filamentous actins are wound together in a helical manner to form the thin filament or the actin filament."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why does the repeated activation of the muscles cause fatigue?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Due to the aerobic breakdown of glycogen",
            "Due to the breakdown of glucose",
            "Due to glycogen formation"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Due to lactic acid accumulation",
        "explanation": "The repeated activation of the muscles leads to the anaerobic breakdown of glycogen. This takes place due to the unavailability of oxygen. This results in the formation of lactic acid, which accumulates and causes fatigue."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these proteins store oxygen?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Troponin",
            "Tropomyosin",
            "\u2018G\u2019 actin"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Myoglobin",
        "explanation": "Myoglobin is present in the muscle fibres. It is red in colour. The function of myoglobin is to store oxygen, so that it is readily available for providing energy in the form of ATP for the proper functioning of muscles."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organelle is abundant in red fibres of muscles?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Sarcoplasmic reticulum",
            "Nuclei",
            "Peroxisomes"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Mitochondria",
        "explanation": "Red fibres of muscle are rich in mitochondria as produce energy in the form of ATP. Red fibres are also rich in myoglobin, which is a red coloured protein that has the function of oxygen storage."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organelle is abundant in white fibres of muscles?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Nuclei",
            "Mitochondria",
            "Peroxisomes"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sarcoplasmic reticulum",
        "explanation": "Muscles contain red fibres and white fibres. The red fibres are rich in myoglobin, which is a red coloured oxygen storing protein, and mitochondria. The white fibres are rich in sarcoplasmic reticulum."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these statements is false regarding white fibres of muscle?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "They contain a large number of sarcoplasmic reticula",
            "They are not rich in myoglobin",
            "They contain fewer mitochondria than red fibres"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "They derive energy from aerobic processes",
        "explanation": "Muscles contain red fibres and white fibres. The white fibres are rich in sarcoplasmic reticulum. They contain a small number of mitochondria and myoglobin. They derive energy from anaerobic processes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Glycolysis is also called ________",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "FMR pathway",
            "LMS pathway",
            "OMS pathway"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "EMP pathway",
        "explanation": "As glycolysis was discovered by three scientists named Embden, Meyerhof and, Parnas, so it also came to be known as the EMP pathway with the initial letters of the discoverers."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is considered as the universal pathway in a biological system?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Krebs cycle",
            "Electron Transport System",
            "Photo Oxidation"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Glycolysis",
        "explanation": "As glycolysis is the beginning step of respiration that occurs in the cytoplasm and due to which the pyruvate is formed, therefore it is considered as the universal pathway in biological systems."
    },
    {
        "question": "In glycolysis, one molecule of glucose is reduced to_______",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "fructose",
            "phosphate",
            "phosphoglycerate"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "pyruvate",
        "explanation": "After the interaction of many co-enzymes and cytochromes, the glucose is at last reduced to two molecules of pyruvic acid which is further reduced to different usable forms in the mitochondria through the Krebs cycle."
    },
    {
        "question": "The net gain of ATP in glycolysis is _____ ATP",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "16",
            "32",
            "4"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "8",
        "explanation": "In glycolysis, two NADH are formed that are equivalent to six ATP. Along with this, there is also the production of 2 more ATP after the transfer of high energy phosphate into ADP adds to this thus making the total of eight."
    },
    {
        "question": "Name the protein that helps pyruvate enter into the mitochondrial matrix",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Contractile protein",
            "Adipose protein",
            "Secretory protein"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Transport protein",
        "explanation": "Pyruvate has to be transported or channeled from the cytoplasm to the mitochondrial matrix. So, transport proteins or channel proteins serve as a means of transport of these molecules across the cellular constituents for further needs."
    },
    {
        "question": "The enzyme that serves as the connecting link between glycolysis and Krebs cycle is ______",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "phosphoenolpyruvic acid",
            "glyceraldehyde",
            "isomerase"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "acetyl CoA",
        "explanation": "Acetyl CoA or activated acetate is formed as a result of the combination of pyruvate with Sulphur containing coenzyme A. This step is also called gateway step or link reaction as it connects the two main processes of respiration namely glycolysis and Krebs cycle."
    },
    {
        "question": "During glycolysis, one NADH is equivalent to _______ number of ATP",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "4",
            "2",
            "1"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "3",
        "explanation": "In glycolysis, two molecules of NADH are formed at the time of oxidation of glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate to 1, 3-diphosphoglycerate which give rise to 6 ATP. This is converted into respective ATP forms during Electron Transport System."
    },
    {
        "question": "The gateway reaction takes place under the enzyme pyruvate dehydrogenase",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "Link reaction or gateway reaction involves the conversion of pyruvic acid into Acetyl CoA after the combination with coenzyme A containing Sulphur. The whole reaction takes place due to the catalyzation effect produced by the enzyme pyruvate dehydrogenase."
    },
    {
        "question": "The scientists that discovered glycolysis are ______",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Hans Kreb and John Dalton",
            "Rudolf Virchow and Robert Brown",
            "Robert Hooke only"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Embden, Meyerhof, and Parnas",
        "explanation": "Glycolysis was discovered by three scientists namely Gustav Embden, Otto Meyerhof and, Jakub Karol Parnas. It can be of many types like homofermentative and heterofermentative pathways."
    },
    {
        "question": "Pyruvic acid and pyruvate are the same substance itself",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "False"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "True",
        "explanation": "Pyruvate is considered as the derivative of pyruvic acid and plays a very important role in sugar metabolism or respiration in living beings. Pyruvate is actually the conjugate base of pyruvic acid but both are considered the same when it comes to as respiratory substrates."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these is not a function of the skeletal system?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Mineral storage",
            "Protection of organs",
            "Movement"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Metabolism",
        "explanation": "The skeletal system is made of bones and cartilages. The skeletal system has several important functions, which include storage of minerals, protection of vital organs, support and movement."
    },
    {
        "question": "What type of tissue is cartilage?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Muscular",
            "Epithelial",
            "Nervous"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Connective",
        "explanation": "The skeletal system is made of bones and cartilages. Both bones and cartilages are specialised connective tissues. Cartilages have a slightly pliable matrix, unlike bones, which possess a hard matrix."
    },
    {
        "question": "The presence of what makes the matrix of bones hard?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Phosphate salts",
            "Chondroitin salts",
            "Sodium salts"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Calcium salts",
        "explanation": "The bones and cartilages that make up our skeletal system are specialised connective tissues. The matrix of bones is hard due to the presence of calcium salts, while that of cartilage is slightly pliable."
    },
    {
        "question": "The presence of what makes the matrix of cartilages slightly pliable?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Phosphate salts",
            "Calcium salts",
            "Sodium salts"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Chondroitin salts",
        "explanation": "The bones and cartilages that make up our skeletal system are specialised connective tissues. The presence of chondroitin salts in the matrix of cartilages is what makes the matrix slightly pliable."
    },
    {
        "question": "How many bones do we have?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "273",
            "206",
            "201"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "270",
        "explanation": "The human body has 206 bones. However, at birth, the human body possesses 270 bones. As we grow up, some of the bones fuse together and hence the number of bones decreases from 270 to 206."
    },
    {
        "question": "How many bones are present in the axial skeleton?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "126",
            "65",
            "106"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "80",
        "explanation": "The bones of the skeletal system are divided into two parts-the axial skeleton and the appendicular skeleton. The axial skeleton consists of 80 bones. These bones are present along the main axis of the body."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these bones are not a part of the axial skeleton?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Skull",
            "Sternum",
            "Ribs"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Clavicle",
        "explanation": "The bones of the skeletal system are divided into two parts- the axial skeleton and the appendicular skeleton. The skull, sternum, vertebral column and ribs make up the axial skeleton of the body."
    },
    {
        "question": "How many facial bones does the skull possess?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "22",
            "8",
            "12"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "14",
        "explanation": "The skull is made up of 22 bones. These bones are classified into two categories- the cranial bones and the facial bones. There are 8 cranial bones and 22 facial bones. The facial bones form the front part of the skull."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the shape of the hyoid bone?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "S \u2013 shape",
            "L \u2013 shape",
            "C \u2013 shape"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "U \u2013 shape",
        "explanation": "The hyoid bone is a U \u2013 shaped bone which is located at the base of the buccal cavity. It is a single bone and is included along with the bones of the skull. The skull possesses a total of 22 bones."
    },
    {
        "question": "The inner ear contains three bones-Malleus, Incus and Stapes",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "True"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "False",
        "explanation": "The middle ear consists of the three bones- Malleus, Incus and Stapes. They are also called the hammer, anvil and stirrup, respectively. The Malleus, Incus and Stapes are collectively called the ear ossicles."
    },
    {
        "question": "How many occipital condyles do humans possess?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "4",
            "1",
            "3"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "2",
        "explanation": "Humans possess two occipital condyles. Hence, humans have a dicondylic skull. The function of the occipital condyles is to articulate the skull region with the superior region of the vertebral column."
    },
    {
        "question": "How many vertebrae do humans possess?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "33",
            "30",
            "22"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "26",
        "explanation": "Humans possess 26 vertebrae in the vertebral column. These vertebrae are divided into five different regions, namely the cervical (7), thoracic (12), lumbar (5), sacral (1-fused) and coccygeal (1-fused) regions."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the central hollow portion of each vertebra known as?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Spinal canal",
            "Vertebral canal",
            "Axial canal"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Neural canal",
        "explanation": "Humans possess 26 vertebrae in the vertebral column. The central hollow portion of each vertebra of the vertebral column is known as the neural canal. The spinal cord passes through the neural canal."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which vertebra articulates with the occipital condyles?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "Axis",
            "Sacral vertebra",
            "Coccygeal vertebra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Atlas",
        "explanation": "Humans possess two occipital condyles. The function of the occipital condyles is to articulate the skull region with the first vertebra of the vertebral column, which is known as the atlas."
    },
    {
        "question": "How many regions is the vertebral column divided into?",
        "incorrect answers": [
            "6",
            "7",
            "4"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "5",
        "explanation": "Humans possess 26 vertebrae in the vertebral column. These vertebrae are divided into five different regions, namely the cervical (7), thoracic (12), lumbar (5), sacral (1-fused) and coccygeal (1-fused) regions."
    }
]